I'm really glad to be here.
أنا سعيد حقًا بوجودي هنا.
I'm glad you're here,
أنا سعيد بوجودكم هنا؛
because that would be a little weird.
وإلا لكان الأمر غريبًا بعض الشيء.
I'm glad we're all here.
أنا سعيد بوجودنا جميعًا هنا،
And by "here," I don't mean here.
وبقولي "هنا" فأنا لا أعني هنا،
Or here.
أو هنا،
But here.
بل هنا؛
I mean Earth.
أعني الأرض.
And by "we," I don't mean those of us in this auditorium,
وبقولي "جميعًا" فأنا لا أعني من بهذا المسرح؛
but life,
بل الحياة،
all life on Earth --
كل أشكال الحياة على الأرض --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
from complex to single-celled,
من المعقد إلى أحادي الخلية،
from mold to mushrooms
من العفن إلى عيش الغراب،
to flying bears.
إلى الدببة الطائرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The interesting thing is,
المثير في الأمر هو
Earth is the only place we know of that has life --
أن الأرض هي المكان الوحيد الذي نعرف أن به حياة --
8.7 million species.
8.7 مليون نوعًا.
We've looked other places,
لقد بحثنا في أماكن أخرى،
maybe not as hard as we should or we could,
ربما لم نبحث بالاجتهاد المرجوّ أو الكافي،
but we've looked and haven't found any;
ولكننا بحثنا ولم نجد.
Earth is the only place we know of with life.
الأرض هي المكان الوحيد الذي نعرف أن به حياة.
Is Earth special?
هل الأرض مميزة؟
This is a question I've wanted to know the answer to
هذا سؤال لطالما أردت معرفة الإجابة عليه
since I was a small child,
منذ أن كنت طفلًا صغيرًا،
and I suspect 80 percent of this auditorium
وأظن أن ثمانين بالمائة من هذا المسرح
has thought the same thing and also wanted to know the answer.
قد فكر بالأمر نفسه وأراد أيضًا معرفة الإجابة.
To understand whether there are any planets --
لكي نفهم إذا ما كان هناك كواكب أخرى --
out there in our solar system or beyond --
هنالك في نظامنا الشمسي أو خارجه --
that can support life,
يمكنها احتواء الحياة،
the first step is to understand what life here requires.
فالخطوة الأول هي أن نفهم ما تتطلبه الحياة.
It turns out, of all of those 8.7 million species,
اتضح أنه، في كل أولئك الأنواع الـ8.7 مليون،
life only needs three things.
تحتاج الحياة لثلاثة أشياء فقط.
On one side, all life on Earth needs energy.
من جانب، تحتاج كل أشكال الحياة على الأرض إلى الطاقة.
Complex life like us derives our energy from the sun,
الحياة المعقدة مثلنا تستمد طاقتنا من الشمس،
but life deep underground can get its energy
لكن الحياة تحت الأرض يمكنها الحصول على طاقتها
from things like chemical reactions.
من مصادر مثل التفاعلات الكيميائية.
There are a number of different energy sources
هناك عدد من مصادر الطاقة المختلفة
available on all planets.
المتوفرة على جميع الكواكب.
On the other side,
من جانب آخر،
all life needs food or nourishment.
كل أشكال الحياة تحتاج إلى طعام أو تغذية،
And this seems like a tall order, especially if you want a succulent tomato.
وهذه تبدو مهمةً صعبة، خصوصًا لو كنت تريد طماطم نضرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
However, all life on Earth derives its nourishment
لكن جميع أشكال الحياة على الأرض تستمد غذاءها
from only six chemical elements,
من ستة عناصر فقط،
and these elements can be found on any planetary body
وهذه العناصر يمكن العثور عليها في أي جسم نباتي
in our solar system.
في مجموعتنا الشمسية.
So that leaves the thing in the middle as the tall pole,
إذن فهذا يضع الأمر في المنتصف كعمودٍ طويل،
the thing that's hardest to achieve.
الأمر الأصعب وصولًا إليه:
Not moose, but water.
ليس غزال الموظ؛ بل الماء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Although moose would be pretty cool.
بالرغم من أن الموظ كان ليكونَ رائعًا.
And not frozen water, and not water in a gaseous state, but liquid water.
وليس ماءً متجمدًا، وليس ماءً في حالة غازية؛ بل ماءً سائلًا.
This is what life needs to survive, all life.
هذا هو ما تحتاجه الحياة للاستمرار، كل أشكال الحياة.
And many solar system bodies don't have liquid water,
والعديد من أجسام النظام الشمسي لا يحتوي على ماء سائل؛
and so we don't look there.
ولذلك لا نبحث هنالك.
Other solar system bodies might have abundant liquid water,
هناك أجسام أخرى في النظام الشمسي ربما تحتوي على ماء سائل وفير،
even more than Earth,
ربما أكثر من الأرض،
but it's trapped beneath an icy shell,
ولكنه منحصر تحت قشرة متجمدة؛
and so it's hard to access, it's hard to get to,
ولذا يصعب الوصول إليه، ويصعب الحصول عليه،
it's hard to even find out if there's any life there.
ويصعب حتى الكشف عما لو أنه توجد حياة هنالك.
So that leaves a few bodies that we should think about.
يتركنا ذلك إذن مع أجسام قليلة ينبغي أن نفكر فيها.
So let's make the problem simpler for ourselves.
لذا دعونا نُبسّط المشكلة على أنفسنا؛
Let's think only about liquid water on the surface of a planet.
دعونا فقط نفكر في ماء سائل على سطح كوكب.
There are only three bodies to think about in our solar system,
هناك ثلاثة أجسام فقط في مجموعتنا الشمسية يمكننا أن نفكر فيها
with regard to liquid water on the surface of a planet,
فيما يخص تواجد ماء سائل على سطح كوكب،
and in order of distance from the sun, it's: Venus, Earth and Mars.
وهم -بالترتيب حسب المسافة من الشمس-: الزهرة، الأرض، والمريخ.
You want to have an atmosphere for water to be liquid.
إنك تريد أن يكون لديك مناخ يسمح للماء أن يظل سائلًا،
You have to be very careful with that atmosphere.
عليك أن تكون حريصًا بشأن المناخ هذا؛
You can't have too much atmosphere, too thick or too warm an atmosphere,
لا ينبغي أن يكون لديك مناخ شديد الكثافة أو السُمك أو الحرارة؛
because then you end up too hot like Venus,
فحينها سينتهي بك الأمر لأن تكون حارًا للغاية مثل الزهرة،
and you can't have liquid water.
ولن يمكنك الحصول على ماء سائل.
But if you have too little atmosphere and it's too thin and too cold,
ولكن لو كان لديك مناخ شديد الرقة أو البرودة،
you end up like Mars, too cold.
فسينتهي بك الأمر مثل المريخ؛ بارد للغاية.
So Venus is too hot, Mars is too cold,
إذن فالزهرة شديد الحرارة، والمريخ شديد البرودة،
and Earth is just right.
والأرض معتدلة تمامًا.
You can look at these images behind me and you can see automatically
يمكنك أن تنظر إلى هذه الصور خلفي وسترى تلقائيًا
where life can survive in our solar system.
أين، في نظامنا الشمسي، يمكن للحياة أن تستمر.
It's a Goldilocks-type problem,
إنها مشكلة تشبه مشكلة Goldilocks
and it's so simple that a child could understand it.
وهي بسيطة لدرجة أنه يمكن لطفل أن يفهمها.
However,
ولكن،
I'd like to remind you of two things
أود أن أذكركم بأمرين
from the Goldilocks story that we may not think about so often
غالبًا ما لا نفكر فيهما من قصة Goldilocks
but that I think are really relevant here.
لكنني أظن أنهما ذوا صلة هنا.
Number one:
الأمر الأول:
if Mama Bear's bowl is too cold
لو أن وعاء الدبة الأم كان شديد البرودة
when Goldilocks walks into the room,
عندما دخل Goldilocks إلى الغرفة،
does that mean it's always been too cold?
هل يعني هذا أنه لطالما كان شديد البرودة؟
Or could it have been just right at some other time?
أو أنه ربما كان معتدلًا في وقت سابق؟
When Goldilocks walks into the room determines the answer
لحظةُ دخول Goldilocks إلى الغرفة تحدد الإجابة
that we get in the story.
التي سنحصل عليها في القصة.
And the same is true with planets.
كذلك الأمر بالنسبة للكواكب؛
They're not static things. They change.
إنهم ليسوا أشياء ثابتة، بل هي تتغير
They vary. They evolve.
تختلف وتتطور،
And atmospheres do the same.
وكذلك الأغلفة الجوية.
So let me give you an example.
لذا دعوني أضرب لكم مثالًا؛
Here's one of my favorite pictures of Mars.
هاكم واحدًا من صوري المفضلة للمريخ،
It's not the highest resolution image, it's not the sexiest image,
إنها ليست الأعلى دقة، ولا الأكثر روعة،
it's not the most recent image,
إنها ليست الصورة الأحدث،
but it's an image that shows riverbeds cut into the surface of the planet;
ولكنها صورة تظهر مجاري الأنهار تشق طريقها على سطح الكوكب،
riverbeds carved by flowing, liquid water;
مجاري نحتَها الماءُ السائل المتدفق؛
riverbeds that take hundreds or thousands or tens of thousands of years to form.
مجاري تحتاج إلى مئات أو آلاف أو العشرات من السنين لتتشكل.
This can't happen on Mars today.
لا يمكن حدوث هذا على المريخ اليوم؛
The atmosphere of Mars today is too thin and too cold
مناخ المريخ اليوم شديد الرقة والبرودة
for water to be stable as a liquid.
بما لا يكفي لاستقرار الماء السائل.
This one image tells you that the atmosphere of Mars changed,
هذه الصورة تخبركم أن مناخ المريخ قد تغير،
and it changed in big ways.
وقد تغير بشكل كبير،
And it changed from a state that we would define as habitable,
وقد تغير عن الحالة التي كانت لِتصنفَه ككوكب صالح للحياة،
because the three requirements for life were present long ago.
لأن المتطلبات الثلاثة الرئيسية للحياة كانت موجودة منذ زمن.
Where did that atmosphere go
أين ذهب هذا الغلاف الجوي
that allowed water to be liquid at the surface?
الذي سمح للماء أن يظل سائلًا على السطح؟
Well, one idea is it escaped away to space.
حسنًا، هناك فكرة تقول أنه هرب إلى الفضاء،
Atmospheric particles got enough energy to break free
جزيئات الغلاف الجوي لديها طاقة كافية للإفلات
from the gravity of the planet,
من جاذبية الكوكب،
escaping away to space, never to return.
هاربةً إلى الفضاء بلا رجعة.
And this happens with all bodies with atmospheres.
وهذا يحدث لكل الأجسام ذات الغلاف الجوي.
Comets have tails
المذنبات لها أذيالٌ
that are incredibly visible reminders of atmospheric escape.
تُعدّ تمثيلًا مرئيًا مدهشًا لإفلات المناخ.
But Venus also has an atmosphere that escapes with time,
لكن الزهرة كذلك به غلاف جوي يُفلت طوال الوقت،
and Mars and Earth as well.
وكذلك المريخ والأرض.
It's just a matter of degree and a matter of scale.
إنها فقط مسألة درجة ونطاق هذا الإفلات.
So we'd like to figure out how much escaped over time
لذلك نود أن نكتشف كم أفلت على مر الزمن؛
so we can explain this transition.
حتى يمكننا توضيح هذا التحول.
How do atmospheres get their energy for escape?
كيف يحصل المناخ على طاقة لللإفلات؟
How do particles get enough energy to escape?
كيف تحصل الذرات على طاقة كافية للإفلات؟
There are two ways, if we're going to reduce things a little bit.
هنالك طريقتين، في حال أردنا أن نبسط الأمور قليلًا.
Number one, sunlight.
الأولى هي أشعة الشمس.
Light emitted from the sun can be absorbed by atmospheric particles
الضوء المنبعث من الشمس يمكن ان يتم امتصاصه من قبل ذرات المناخ
and warm the particles.
فيُسخن الذرات.
Yes, I'm dancing, but they --
نعم، أنا أرقص؛ لكنهم --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Oh my God, not even at my wedding.
يا إلهي، ليس حتى في زفافي.
They get enough energy to escape and break free
يحصلون على طاقة كافية للهروب والإفلات
from the gravity of the planet just by warming.
من جاذبية الكوكب فقط باكتساب الحرارة.
A second way they can get energy is from the solar wind.
الطريقة الأخرى للحصول على الطاقة هي الرياح الشمسية؛
These are particles, mass, material, spit out from the surface of the sun,
وهي ذرات، كتلة، مادة تنطلق من على سطح الشمس
and they go screaming through the solar system
وتذهب صارخةً خلال النظام الشمسي
at 400 kilometers per second,
بسرعة 400 كيلومترًا في الثانية،
sometimes faster during solar storms,
وأحيانًا أسرع خلال العواصف الشمسية،
and they go hurtling through interplanetary space
تندفع خلال الفضاء
towards planets and their atmospheres,
تجاه الكواكب وأغلفتها الجوية
and they may provide energy
وربما يمدون ذرات الغلاف الجوي
for atmospheric particles to escape as well.
بالطاقة اللازمة للإفلات أيضًا.
This is something that I'm interested in,
هذا أمر يثير اهتمامي
because it relates to habitability.
لأنه مرتبط بالصلاحية للحياة.
I mentioned that there were two things about the Goldilocks story
ذكرت أن هناك أمرين بخصوص قصة Goldilocks
that I wanted to bring to your attention and remind you about,
أردت أن أجلب انتباهكم وأذكركم بهما؛
and the second one is a little bit more subtle.
والأمر الثاني أكثر تعقيدًا.
If Papa Bear's bowl is too hot,
لو أن وعاء الدب الأب كان ساخنًا للغاية،
and Mama Bear's bowl is too cold,
ووعاء الدبة الأم كان باردًا للغاية،
shouldn't Baby Bear's bowl be even colder
ألم يكن ينبغي على وعاء الدب الطفل أن يكون أكثر برودة
if we're following the trend?
لو أننا سنسير حسب السياق؟
This thing that you've accepted your entire life,
هذا الأمر الذي قبلت به طوال حياتك،
when you think about it a little bit more, may not be so simple.
حين تفكر فيه أكثر قليلًا، ربما لا يبدو بهذه البساطة.
And of course, distance of a planet from the sun determines its temperature.
وبالطبع، المسافة بين الكوكب والشمس تحدد درجة حرارته،
This has to play into habitability.
وهذا له تأثير على صلاحيته للحياة.
But maybe there are other things we should be thinking about.
ولكن ربما هناك أشياء أخرى ينبغي أن نفكر بها،
Maybe it's the bowls themselves
ربما هي الأوعية نفسها
that are also helping to determine the outcome in the story,
التي تساعد أيضًا في تحديد مغزى القصة،
what is just right.
ما هو المعتدل الصحيح.
I could talk to you about a lot of different characteristics
يمكنني أن أتحدث لكم عن الكثير من الخصائص المختلفة
of these three planets
لهؤلاء الكواكب الثلاثة
that may influence habitability,
يمكن أن تؤثر على صلاحيتهم للحياة،
but for selfish reasons related to my own research
لكن لأسباب أنانية مرتبطة ببحثي
and the fact that I'm standing up here holding the clicker and you're not --
ولحقيقة أنني أقف هنا أحمل الناقر وليس أنتم --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I would like to talk for just a minute or two
أود أن أحدثكم لدقيقة أو اثنتَين
about magnetic fields.
عن المجالات المغناطيسية.
Earth has one; Venus and Mars do not.
الأرض لديها واحدًا؛ الزهرة والمريخ لا.
Magnetic fields are generated in the deep interior of a planet
المجالات المغناطيسية تتولد في الباطن العميق للكوكب
by electrically conducting churning fluid material
عن طريق التوصيل الكهربائي لمادة سائلة هائجة
that creates this big old magnetic field that surrounds Earth.
تخلق المجال المغناطيسي القديم والكبير هذا الذي يحوط الأرض.
If you have a compass, you know which way north is.
لو أن لديك بوصلة فستعرف أي اتجاه هو الشمال،
Venus and Mars don't have that.
الزهرة والمريخ لا يمتلكان ذلك.
If you have a compass on Venus and Mars,
لو أن لديك بوصلة على الزهرة أو المريخ،
congratulations, you're lost.
فهنيئًا لك؛ أنت تائه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Does this influence habitability?
هل يؤثر هذا على الصلاحية للحياة؟
Well, how might it?
حسنًا، ما احتمالية ذلك؟
Many scientists think that a magnetic field of a planet
علماء عديدون يرون أن المجال المغناطيسي للكوكب
serves as a shield for the atmosphere,
يعمل كدرع لغلافه الجوي،
deflecting solar wind particles around the planet
يعكس ذرات الرياح الشمسية بعيدًا عن الكوكب
in a bit of a force field-type effect
بتأثير قوة لها طابع المجال
having to do with electric charge of those particles.
مرتبطة بالشحنات الكهربائية لهذه الذرات.
I like to think of it instead as a salad bar sneeze guard for planets.
لكنني أفضل أن أراه على أنه زجاج حامٍ لقسم السلطات؛ فقط للكواكب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And yes, my colleagues who watch this later will realize
وأجل، زملائي ممن سيشاهدون هذا لاحقًا سيدركون
this is the first time in the history of our community
أن هذه هي المرة الأولى في تاريخ مجتمعنا
that the solar wind has been equated with mucus.
حيث يتم تشبيه الرياح الشمسية بالمخاط.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
OK, so the effect, then, is that Earth may have been protected
حسنًا، فالنتيجة إذن أن الأرض ربما كانت محمية
for billions of years,
لمليارات السنين
because we've had a magnetic field.
لأننا لدينا مجال مغناطيسي.
Atmosphere hasn't been able to escape.
الغلاف الجوي لم يكن قادرًا على الإفلات.
Mars, on the other hand, has been unprotected
المريخ، على الجانب الآخر، كان غير محميّ
because of its lack of magnetic field,
لأنه يفتقد للمجال المغناطيسي،
and over billions of years,
وعلى مدار مليارات السنين
maybe enough atmosphere has been stripped away
ربما تم تجريده من غلافه الجوي بما يكفي
to account for a transition from a habitable planet
لكي يتسبب في تحويله من كوكب صالح للحياة
to the planet that we see today.
إلى الكوكب الذي نراه اليوم.
Other scientists think that magnetic fields
يعتقد علماء آخرون أن المجال المغناطيسي
may act more like the sails on a ship,
ربما يعمل بطريقة أشبه بأشرعةٍ على مركب،
enabling the planet to interact with more energy from the solar wind
حيث يمكّن الكوكب من التفاعل مع مقدار طاقة من الرياح الشمسية
than the planet would have been able to interact with by itself.
أكبر مما كان الكوكب لِيتفاعلَ معه بمفرده.
The sails may gather energy from the solar wind.
هذه الأشرعة يمكنها تجميع طاقة من الرياح الشمسية.
The magnetic field may gather energy from the solar wind
المجال مغناطيسي يمكنه تجميع طاقة من الرياح الشمسية
that allows even more atmospheric escape to happen.
مما يسمح بحدوث مزيد من إفلات الغلاف الجوي.
It's an idea that has to be tested,
إنها فكرة لابد من اختبارها،
but the effect and how it works
ولكن أثرها وكيفية عملها
seems apparent.
يبدوان واضحان.
That's because we know
هذا بسبب أننا نعلم أن
energy from the solar wind is being deposited into our atmosphere
الطاقة من الرياح الشمسية يتم ترسيبها في غلافنا الجوي؛
here on Earth.
هنا على الأرض.
That energy is conducted along magnetic field lines
هذه الطاقة تتم قيادتها بطول خطوط المجال المغناطيسي
down into the polar regions,
لأسفل حيث المناطق القطبية،
resulting in incredibly beautiful aurora.
حيث تتسبب في شفق قطبي رائع الجمال.
If you've ever experienced them, it's magnificent.
إذا كنت قد اختبرت الأمر فستعلم أنه رائع.
We know the energy is getting in.
إننا نعلم أن الطاقة تدخل.
We're trying to measure how many particles are getting out
ونحاول أن نقيس كم من الذرات يخرج،
and if the magnetic field is influencing this in any way.
وما إذا كان المجال المغناطيسي يؤثر على الأمر بأي طريقة،
So I've posed a problem for you here,
لذلك فقد قدمت إليكم مشكلة هنا،
but I don't have a solution yet.
لكنني لا أمتلك حلًا لها بعد.
We don't have a solution.
إننا لا نمتلك حلًا،
But we're working on it. How are we working on it?
لكننا نعمل على إيجاده.
Well, we've sent spacecraft to all three planets.
حسنًا، لقد بعثنا بمركبة فضائية للكواكب الثلاثة.
Some of them are orbiting now,
بعضهم لا يزال في المدار،
including the MAVEN spacecraft which is currently orbiting Mars,
بما فيهم مركبة MAVEN التي تدور حول المريخ حاليًا،
which I'm involved with and which is led here,
والتي شاركت فيها والتي يتم قيادتها من هنا؛
out of the University of Colorado.
خارج جامعة كولورادو.
It's designed to measure atmospheric escape.
إنها مصممة لقياس مدى إفلات الغلاف الجوي.
We have similar measurements from Venus and Earth.
لدينا قياسات مشابهة من الزهرة والأرض.
Once we have all our measurements,
متى حصلنا على كل القياسات،
we can combine all these together, and we can understand
فيمكننا أن نجمع بين جميعهم، ويمكننا أن نفهم
how all three planets interact with their space environment,
كيف يتفاعل الكواكب الثلاثة مع البيئة الفضائية،
with the surroundings.
مع ما يحيط بهم.
And we can decide whether magnetic fields are important for habitability
ويمكننا أن نقرر ما إذا كان المجال المغناطيسي مهمًا للصلاحية للحياة،
or not.
أو لا.
Once we have that answer, why should you care?
متى حصلنا على الإجابة، لماذا يجب أن نهتم؟
I mean, I care deeply ...
أعني، أنا مهتم بشدة ...
And financially as well, but deeply.
وماليًا أيضًا، ولكن بشدة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
First of all, an answer to this question
بدايةً، الإجابة على هذا السؤال
will teach us more about these three planets,
ستعلمنا الكثير عن هذه الكواكب الثلاثة:
Venus, Earth and Mars,
الزهرة والأرض والمريخ،
not only about how they interact with their environment today,
ليس فقط عن كيفية تفاعلهم مع محيطهم اليوم،
but how they were billions of years ago,
ولكن أيضًا كيف كانوا منذ مليارات السنين؛
whether they were habitable long ago or not.
ما إذا كانو صالحين للحياة قديمًا أم لا.
It will teach us about atmospheres
ستعلمنا عن الأغلفة الجوية
that surround us and that are close.
التي تحيط بنا والقريبة منا.
But moreover, what we learn from these planets
بل أكثر من ذلك، ما سنتعلمه من هذه الكواكب
can be applied to atmospheres everywhere,
يمكن تطبيقه على الأغلفة الجوية في أي مكان،
including planets that we're now observing around other stars.
بما فيها الكواكب التي نلاحظها الآن حول النجوم.
For example, the Kepler spacecraft,
مثلًا، مركبة Kepler الفضائية
which is built and controlled here in Boulder,
التي تم بناؤها ويتم التحكم بها من هنا في بولدر،
has been observing a postage stamp-sized region of the sky
لاحظتْ على مدار السنتين الماضيين منطقة في السماء
for a couple years now,
بحجم طابع بريد،
and it's found thousands of planets --
وعثرتْ على آلالف من الكواكب --
in one postage stamp-sized region of the sky
في منطقة واحد من السماء بحجم طابع بريد
that we don't think is any different from any other part of the sky.
لا نعتقد أنها تختلف عن أي جزء آخر من السماء.
We've gone, in 20 years,
لقد تقدمنا في عشرين سنة،
from knowing of zero planets outside of our solar system,
من عدم معرفة كوكب واحد خارج نظامنا الشمسي،
to now having so many,
إلى معرفة الكثير منها الآن،
that we don't know which ones to investigate first.
لدرجة أننا لا نعرف أيهم سنتقصى أولًا.
Any lever will help.
أي رافعة ستساعد.
In fact, based on observations that Kepler's taken
في الحقيقة، طبقًا للملاحظات التي أخذتها Kepler
and other similar observations,
وبعض الملاحظات الأخرى المشابهة،
we now believe that,
إننا نؤمن الآن أنه
of the 200 billion stars in the Milky Way galaxy alone,
من ضمن 200 مليار نجمة في مجرة درب التبانة وحدها،
on average, every star has at least one planet.
فلدى كل نجمة يوجد، في المعدل، كوكب واحد على الأقل.
In addition to that,
بالإضافة إلى ذلك،
estimates suggest there are somewhere between 40 billion and 100 billion
تقترح التقديرات أنه يوجد في مكان ما ما بين 40 مليار إلى 100 مليار
of those planets that we would define as habitable
من هذه الكواكب التي يمكن اعتبارها صالحة للحياة
in just our galaxy.
في مجرتنا فقط.
We have the observations of those planets,
لدينا هذه الملاحظات من أولئك الكواكب،
but we just don't know which ones are habitable yet.
ولكننا لا نعلم بعد أيهم صالح للحياة.
It's a little bit like being trapped on a red spot --
الأمر يشبه قليلًا أن تكون عالقًا ببقعة حمراء --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
on a stage
على المسرح،
and knowing that there are other worlds out there
وتعلم أن هناك عوالم أخرى في الخارج،
and desperately wanting to know more about them,
وتريد بشدة معرفة المزيد عنهم،
wanting to interrogate them and find out if maybe just one or two of them
تريد أن تستوجبهم وتعلم ما إذا ربما كان واحد أو اثنان منهم
are a little bit like you.
يشبهونك بعض الشيء.
You can't do that. You can't go there, not yet.
لا يمكنك فعل ذلك؛ لا يمكنك الذهاب هناك، ليس بعد،
And so you have to use the tools that you've developed around you
ولذلك فعليك استخدام الأدوات التي طورتها حولك
for Venus, Earth and Mars,
لأجل الزهرة والأرض والمريخ،
and you have to apply them to these other situations,
وعليك أن تطبقها على هذه المواقف الأخرى،
and hope that you're making reasonable inferences from the data,
وتأمل أنك تتوصل إلى استنتاجات منطقية من البيانات،
and that you're going to be able to determine the best candidates
وأنك ستكون قادرًا على تحديد المرشحين الأفضل
for habitable planets, and those that are not.
ليكونوا كواكب صالحة حياة، والذين هم غير صالحين.
In the end, and for now, at least,
في النهاية، وللآن على الأقل،
this is our red spot, right here.
هذه هي بقعتنا الحمراء، هنا.
This is the only planet that we know of that's habitable,
هذا هو الكوكب الوحيد الذي نعرف أنه صالح للحياة،
although very soon we may come to know of more.
بالرغم من أنه في القريب العاجل ربما سنعرف المزيد.
But for now, this is the only habitable planet,
ولكن للآن، هذا هو الكوكب الوحيد الصالح للحياة،
and this is our red spot.
هذه هي بقعتنا الحمراء.
I'm really glad we're here.
أنا سعيد حقًا بأننا هنا.
Thanks.
شكرًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)